Guide to Dillingham Family papers, 1858-1958 MS 257
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Dillingham Family papers
1858-1958
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Dillingham family
MS 257
3.5 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
The Dillingham Family Papers, consisting of approximately 900 items or 1.25 linear feet, follows the history of a prominent Texas family from 1858 to 1958. Correspondence, manuscripts, printed material, photographs, journals, poetry, and newspaper clippings show the life style of a family who moved into Texas during the prosperous era of the late nineteenth century and played an important role in developing both the social and economic framework of Houston.
Biographical Note
Three Dillingham brothers "came to Salem with Winthrop in 1630" from Leicestershire in England. A member of the fourth generation, Paul Dillingham (1799-1891) lived in Waterbury, Vermont where he was a member of the State Bar, president of the bank, and later governor of the state. He had four sons and a daughter by his wife Julia Carpenter Dillingham.
One of their sons, Edwin (1839-1864), a captain in the Union Army, was killed at the battle of Winchester. Another son, William Paul, became a U. S. Senator. He served as chairman of the Committee on Immigration for several years and was an influential member of Congress. A third son, Frank (1848-?), moved to Texas where he was in the railroad business.
After serving as a colonel in the Union Army, Charles Dillingham moved to New Orleans where he stayed until 1885. At that time he moved to Houston as receiver of Houston and Texas Central Railway. When the South Texas National Bank was formed, he became first vice-president and later was promoted to president, then chairman of the board. In 1863 Charles married Frances M. Cutter of Cleveland, Ohio, and they had two children, a son Edwin Kirke, and a daughter Mary Pauline.
Pauline, or "Pucky" as her friends and family often called her, remained unmarried and devoted most of her time to her brother's family. She also wrote both poetry and fiction and had several pieces published. In poor health much of her life, Pauline usually spent summers at a family home in Camden, Maine escaping the stifling Houston weather. The rest of the year she lived with Edwin and his family in Houston and occasionally took trips abroad. In 1959, she and her brother donated their stately family home on Austin Street to the Child Guidance Council.
Pauline's brother, Edwin K. Dillingham, married Charlotte (Lottie) Porter, and they had two children, Elizabeth Randon and Charles. Elizabeth went to School in the east and married James Hart of New York City where the couple lived. Charles went to Yale and married Barbara Kibler with whom he had a son, Charles.
Scope and Contents
The collection of the Dillingham Family Papers, consisting of approximately 900 items or 1.25 linear feet, follows the history of a prominent Texas family from 1858 to 1958. Correspondence, manuscripts, printed material, photographs, journals, poetry, and newspaper clippings show the life style of a family who moved into Texas during the prosperous era of the late nineteenth century and played an important role in developing both the social and economic framework of Houston.
The main portion of the collection is correspondence between various family members, with most written by the children and grandchildren of Charles K. Dillingham, who settled in Houston and played an integral part in the development of a predecessor bank of the Texas Commerce Bank. He, his wife Frances Cutter Dillingham, and their two children, Edwin K. and Mary Pauline, were very active socially, and the Dillingham name remains important in Houston.
Originally from Vermont, some of the members of the Dillingham family remained there and contributed to the prosperity of that state. Paul Dillingham was governor of Vermont, and his son William served as a United States Senator for several years. Both the personal and business papers of these men are included in the collection.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.Stored off-site at Iron Mountain and requires 48-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift of the Dillingham family on 3 June 1966.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged chronologically with respect to the individuals involved. Most letters are filed according to the person who wrote them, unless there are only one or two from an individual, in which case the letter is filed according to whom it was sent.
General Note
Portions of this collection are available online at: "https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/21715" "Dillingham Family papers" https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/21715
Index Terms
Subjects
Legislators; Governors -- United States; Banks and banking; Frontier life
Document Types
journals (accounts); clippings (information artifacts); photographs; manuscripts (document genre); corrrespondence
Places
United States; Texas -- Houston; Vermont
Subjects (Persons)
Dillingham, Paul; Dillingham, William; Dillingham, Charles K.; Dillingham, Frances Cutter
- Series I: Genealogy, 185027
  - Dillingham Genealogy, 1630-1934; 11676 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Letters, photographs, diaries and ephemera, 185028
  - Paul Dillingham (Gov.), includes 2 photos, 1863-1879; 11675 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edwin Dillingham (Major), Commissions, Military Correspondence (including official correspondence re: his death; family correspondence), 1862-1865; 11674 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - William Paul Dillingham Correspondence, includes 2 Calvin Coolidge letters, 1885-1917; 11673 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - William Paul Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1887-1915; 11672 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William Paul Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1890-1916; 11671 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Paul Dillingham - Miscellaneous, includes 2 photos, 1900-1923; 11670 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Charles Dillingham to Fannie Cutter Dillingham, 1858-1916; 11669 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Charles Dillingham to Edwin Dillingham, 1861-1864; 11668 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Charles Dillingham to Paul Dillingham, 1861-1865; 11667 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charles Dillingham to Julia C. Dillingham, 1861-1869; 11666 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Julia C. Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1870-1895; 11665 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dillingham Clipping Book [?], 11664 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, n. d.; 11663 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Charles Dillingham ephemeral items, 1861-1917; 11662 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Charles Dillingham Photographs (8), 1863-[?]; 11661 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Charles Dillingham to Edwin Dillingham, 1879-1911; 11660 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Charles Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1883-1912; 11659 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Charles Dillingham Business Papers, 1896-1915; 11658 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Imprints - 8th Vermont Association Constitution and By-Laws, Year Book of Christ Church Parish, Houston, The Harvest Carnival Ball Program; Sweeny & Coombs Opera House Official Program, Dedicatory Service First Presbyterian Church, The Legend of Houston, Kinkaid Almanac, 1888-1933 1888; 1902; 21 November 1893; 31 March 1901; 1933; 5 December 1924; 11657 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Charles Dillingham Clippings, 189[?]-1917; 11656 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Frances C. Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1863-1916; 11655 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Frances C. Dillingham to Various Family Members, 1863-1925; 11654 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Fannie Dillingham from Family and Friends, 1890-1927; 11653 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Diary of Frances Cutter Dillingham, 1867; 11652 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Frances C. Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1886-1912; 11651 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Journal of Frances C. Dillingham, 1899 June-Aug; 11650 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Journal of Frances C. Dillingham, 1899 Sept-Oct; 11649 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Journal of Frances C. Dillingham, 1906-1907; 11648 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Recipes - Fannie Dillingham, n. d.; 11647 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arthur Cutter to Fannie Cutter Dillingham, 1892-[1909]; 11646 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arthur Cutter to Pauline Dillingham, 1889-1893; 11645 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Various Family Members to Pauline Dillingham, 1891-1893; 11644 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pauline Dillingham to Various Family Members, 1892-1934; 11643 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pauline Dillingham - Miscellaneous, 1892-1942; 11642 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Psychology Notebook of Pauline Dillingham, 1893; 11641 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Poems of Mary Pauline Dillingham compiled by Charlotte Dillingham, 1897; 11640 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Between Pauline Dillingham and Horace Clark, 1910-1944; 11639 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Songs by Horace Clark, 1914; 11638 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pauline Dillingham to Frances C. Dillingham, 1926; 11637 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pauline Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1929; 11636 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pauline Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1933-1941; 11635 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pauline Dillingham Business Papers, 1934-1942; 11634 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Various Poetry Editors to Pauline Dillingham, 1935-1939; 11633 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Manuscripts of Poems and Short Stories by Pauline Dillingham, 11632 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pauline Dillingham Clippings, n. d.; 11631 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Draft of Will of Pauline Dillingham, n. d.; 11630 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Edwin K. Dillingham to Arthur Cutter, 1876; 11629 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Edwin K. Dillingham - Miscellaneous, 1879-1957; 11628 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Edwin K. Dillingham to Various Family Members, 1889-1926; 11627 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Edwin K. Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1890-1944; 11626 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1926-1945; 11625 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Edwin K. Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1929; 11624 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lottie Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1909-1940; 11623 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lottie Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1929; 11622 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Lottie Dillingham, 1925-1929; 11621 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Lottie Dillingham, 1930-1933; 11620 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Lottie Dillingham, 1934-1956; 11619 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1923-1929; 11618 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1930-1933; 11617 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1935-1955; 11616 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Parents, 1923-1929; 11615 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Parents, 1930-1932; 11614 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Parents, 1933-1952; 11613 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1928-1942; 11612 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Charles Dillingham, 1925-[?]; 11611 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth Dillingham to Grandma Dillingham, [?}-1925; 11610 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Poems by Elizabeth Randon Dillingham, [?]-1930; 11609 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - James Hart to Mr. and Mrs. E. K. Dillingham, 1930-1952; 11608 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Charles Dillingham to Lottie Dillingham, 1926-1929; 11607 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Charles Dillingham to Lottie Dillingham, 1930-1931; 11606 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Charles Dillingham to Lottie Dillingham, 1932-1937; 11605 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Charles Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1926-1929; 11604 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Charles Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1930-1933; 11603 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Charles Dillingham to Edwin K. Dillingham, 1934-1943; 11602 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Charles Dillingham to Parents, 1926-1929; 11601 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Charles Dillingham to Parents, 1930-1932; 11600 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Charles Dillingham to Parents, 1933-1958; 11599 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Charles Dillingham to Pauline Dillingham, 1930-1942; 11598 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Charles Dillingham, includes photo, 19[?]-1929; 11597 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - From Barbara and Charles Dillingham, 1940-1952; 11596 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - From Chuck Dillingham, 1948-1958; 11595 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Various letters and fragments, 11594 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Letters to Lottie Dillingham, 1927-1954; 11593 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1891-1941; 11592 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1886-; 11591 (Box 7, Folder 3)